we have 45 minutes okay just hang in
there learn the deep DCI teacher secret
how to sleep in the class with your eyes
open okay the people who didn't finish
the DCI teacher training they will go
but the real teachers will look like
that what do the super advanced teachers
do now they go like this every five
minutes then definitely they look like
they're away you know so I'm just
teaching you this this is a high teacher
skill okay all right you can practice it
tomorrow or tonight okay I'm gonna go to
your homework we're just here somewhere
okay I would like to teach this class in
the traditional way okay I don't want to
just go through the homework okay so one
class let's do it the old way okay just
for fun I looked at this class and I
said it would be fun to teach this class
the real the real way okay so I'm gonna
do it the real way okay you okay with
that probably take the rest of tonight
and then tomorrow
okay so we're behind as usual Tim - I
promised him I wouldn't do this but I
did
[Music]
yeah okay here we go
I'm gonna teach it the old way okay
ready aoyama-san continuously dominant a
noble um Camden pattern angry - Motegi
tunisian dougie shepherd cha this is a
very famous part of the three principal
house
okay p le right Tim yelled at me cuz
kids are you didn't fix your own mistake
in the homework I said I'm sorry you'll
all have to do it with your pencil or
whatever okay all right so this is one
of the important beginning lines of the
three principles and I'd like to go
through it with you in a traditional way
okay
garrison of convening burden I'm gonna
teach you the very heart of all the
teachings of the Buddhist okay first
line I'm gonna teach you the heart of
all the teachings of the Buddha scale
say dumpin on King not Balaam I'm gonna
teach you the path which all the body
suffers think is so cool that's the
second line okay third line Camden
Tottenham did you know today I'm gonna
help you enter the jungle
okay jamoke means a special word right a
word for a hundred dollars
damn to slow down you make you're making
me poor okay yeah it means in Tibet
there's many many rivers because there's
no anywhere and there's no bridges
because they didn't have cement and
steel until now so you had to find the
shallow part to ride your horse over and
that's called um okay it means an easy
place to enter a stream an easier place
to go across so he some copper calls his
own book this is the general for people
have really good karma okay and who art
under panda
who want to reach enlightenment Thunder
okay why don't why am i emphasizing
Tunde that's Keshe load tars real name
so if you want to impress him you can
say we studied time through the other
nine he'll go oh that's my name you say
really okay
his name is well say Lobsang time dude
okay who seeks for freedom okay what's
the love song you're mine where did he
get the name yeah
camera matches first name he inherited
okay he made him a month okay okay then
the last line gee tarnation ducky
shippers are said jitta nation ducky
Shepard cha okay by the way many people
come to me and say I would like to learn
Tibetan and it's a good idea okay now
listen
and there's we we have three teams
trying to find the Sanskrit originals
okay which were destroyed in India maybe
we think we can find a hundred we have
three teams they've been working for
twelve years we've been paying them for
twelve years
big teams and they they only input like
less than a hundred books okay it's very
difficult to find the Sanskrit books
okay in the Tibetan language including
the originals from India there are three
hundred thousand books each one is
incredible
no no fluff what is he there's no
detective novels in Tibetan language
it's a hundred percent heavy duty
incredible books okay it's a lot by far
the largest spiritual literary tradition
in the world okay people just don't know
about it
John Brady's working to stop that
okay why did I brag about that I don't
remember yeah oh yeah so people ask me
they want to learn to button memorize
this poem it's 14 verses okay it takes
about two minutes to recite okay and and
normally the books we memorize are an
hour and a half to recite two hours to
be site you can recite this one in a
bone I don't know three minutes okay
so if you're interested to learn Tibetan
learn the prayers first you know sushi
Oh Sachi and learn those first okay and
then go on to this book okay this is
easy okay fourteen verses and I'd like
Nick he asked me how can I start my
Tibetan I said memorize this and he did
and his Tibetan is pretty good now okay
so it puts a big seed in your mind okay
by the way I think Jenny's coming to the
translation you're all welcome to come
to the translation course you don't have
to be a translator
we have secondary translators who are
going to translate the English into
Spanish Russian German French Mandarin
okay you're always welcome to come to
the college it's tough okay it's tough
it's it's I don't know five hours a day
six hours a day heavy heavy heavy but
your mind will grow like really big okay
then you can teach like Stanley okay
I'm not kidding okay he's got all this
stuff in there that's gonna grow his
head got bigger already
I'm trying to give them a lot of pride
so I can break it later okay
so the last verse means that the last
line is cheater initiative Japanese I
will do my best to explain why the
essence of all the Buddhist teaching to
the path that all the Buddhist Sufis
think is super sexy number three the
entry point for those who want to go to
freedom I will explain it you know as
best as I can
he goes like this some copper goes as
you know I'm just a dummy okay and
that's a traditional way to start a
scripture
it's called say Kimba Kim kanga Kim
Geshe Michael says get up on the altar
get up on the throne teacher abhidharma
mental functions whatever okay
traditionally the first thing you do
traditionally for 2,000 years you get up
on the throne and you say I have all
these negative emotions more than anyone
in this room and thank you for letting
me teach and Geshe Michael says to you
tonight thank you for letting me teach I
know you're all Buddhist I know I'm the
only not Buddha in the room and it's fun
to teach so thank you for that and I'll
do the best I can
okay so some copper is being what do you
call humble okay but it's true also and
never forget it you're gonna be an HDI
teacher right it's very possible that
every student you ever meet is already a
Buddha and they're just trying to get
you to talk about it okay if Geshe
Michael talks about jealousy 10,000
times in 40 years maybe he'll get it
don't look so do de okay just go like
I'm not a Buddha geshe-la
maybe this other guy is sorry okay
anyway thanks for letting me teach
so that's traditional by the way what's
the other thing happening in that line
traditionally
he's promising to finish the book and
this is a comment on Buddhist
commitments okay and this is
traditionally one of the most serious
commitments of Buddhist can make I
pledge to teach this class I will make
you do these yoga poses in the same
order over and over again unless I die
before the end of the class you see
that's a commitment okay it's a Buddhist
teachers commitment okay I will
so you're going to go to your own
students this year right you can say I'm
going to teach you class of course one
and in your mind you got to say I will
not quit unless I die okay and that's
very interesting in the canon in the
scriptures there are books that end
halfway through a sentence why the guy
died okay got hit by a car or whatever
elephants okay and it's considered one
of the most serious promises you can
make like sadie's gonna finish his
canonized translation or die trying okay
and and it's always in the first verse
it's always in the first verse I I will
do it I will complete this I promise I
will finish or I will die first
okay Stanley's gonna have to he's got
like 25 years good luck okay alright now
that big how much time we got
[Music]
okay good we still have half an hour the
big fish on Bank thing about this verse
say John cool same the cool thing about
the first verse of the three principal
paths is that some copper anyone I guess
what he did he put the three principal
paths in the first verse he hid them in
the first verse okay it's we already
covered the three principal paths so I
give you permission to memorize the
three principal paths by just memories
in the first verse
you can play jokes on people you want to
hear me recite than three pencil passes
yeah
then just say the first verse didn't I
say but there's 13 more verses you say
no the first verse has everything in it
Papa guy said so it's true okay let's
look at it okay ready
and I'm gonna switch to English okay as
far as I'm able I will explain okay
which line last line okay Tibetan syntax
and English syntax is opposite okay
in Tibetan you say to the store go I
will to the store go I will okay
so you have to translate the last line
first I promise I will write this book
which is the essence of all the high
teachings of the Buddha's okay what's
that
which of the three principal paths
renunciation
miss miss run off I looked it up you
asked me nice runner yeah in Sanskrit
Nik means definitely like Matata and
Rana you know from prasarita or they
call it spread your legs are prasarita
what part of the nephron asana anyway
possibly that means spread out the word
sansara comes from the same root
spread out can also mean to flow in a
straight line okay
the word surge comes from that and the
word right comes from that and there
used to be a G on the end of it and
that's why right is spelled with a CH
arrow gh written in German hey you don't
care okay so the essence of all the high
teachings of the victors is renunciation
I'm tired I'm tired okay I'm tired
there's too much pain in this world you
know yoga teachers giving pain to their
students
just kidding I like to make fun of
Andres okay the path that all their holy
children recommend by the way I
translated this so long ago you were
supposed to say the male pronoun he and
I'm going back and changing them all
today okay but I didn't get there okay
so who's the children of the Buddhist
buddy suffice what's this Tibetan for
that girl say okay we named her when I
gave I gave you the name I think it's
child you are the child of the Buddhist
okay
it means buddy supper okay so guess
which of the three principle pass is the
path that the Bodhisattvas recommend is
yeah bodhichitta the wish to become a
buddha so you can help billions of
planets okay alright and that's the
entry point for those who want to reach
enlightenment what's that a secret we
referring to there's only one left
yeah emptiness understanding the pen
okay the last line is about the pen if
someone teaches to the pen correctly you
entered the ocean you you started across
the stream okay you might get free okay
so the three prince of bats are already
hidden in the first verse so I could
actually stop the class early but I'm
not gonna as you knew okay
mmm now I'm just gonna go through you
know sweet points he talks about the
first line which is the essence of all
the teachings of the Buddhist and the
way he wants to talk about it pop on
command pitcher in his commentary is
that he wants to talk about what's not
the teaching of the Buddhist so it's
interesting that on the same day our
morning long room and our evening long
room hit the same point which is don't
waste your valuable mental real estate
don't infect it with a wrong idea that's
going to stay there for 10,000 years
okay be careful what you study okay so
that's a subject here and they have a
letter than they put a letter that
tsongkhapa wrote a llama oom Appa
anybody except word for $100 whose llama
whom Appa yeah okay let's go let's go
yeah she's got she got it she should
know anyway don't tell her I didn't
losing money for me Rani
oh that's dumb erection
okay you want the hundred dollars you're
like the director that's not fair okay
go ahead I'll pay for your lunch yeah
what was his occupation he was a
shepherd in the mountains
okay and he was just a plain old dirty
shepherd and people said he had met
manjushri directly so there's a story
that tsongkhapa went to him and he said
did you really meet Madhu she directly
can you have really direct line to you
know manjushri and whom opposite yep
he's like this old man dirty Shepherd
you know he said yeah I have a direct
line and so Kapil says do you mind if I
just ask you some questions to check if
you're telling the truth
I think if I was a llama mop I would
have said go to hell but uh but llama
mapless say okay he asked me some
questions
and so Tonkawa asked him all these super
difficult points about emptiness you
know like what's what's the mind only
version of emptiness between
consciousness seven and consciousness
you know and then Maupassant
oh you know and he gave every time he
gave a perfect answer
so some copper I used to go to him to
get advice from mungeri and then
guess what he did after that like a year
later yes he said they were month but
you know it's a waste of time to me
climb up here be with all these stinky
sheep why don't you just teach me how to
do that and he did and they say that's
why it's on copper wrote such good stuff
okay
direct line to manjushri alright later
people said he is Montrachet okay we
made 713 chairman Jimin can be one more
jump young okay so anyway he wrote a
letter to a mapa and in the letter he
said you know what people are asking me
to teach all the time and I decided to
just teach our teachers to page long
room and I called what buddy Potter
pradipika but that's the same in English
yeah light on the path in line he said
you know what I realized
so he's writing to his old mentor you
know ten years later and he says now I'm
a famous teacher everyone's asking me to
teach I get invitations everywhere and I
figured out the best thing to teach
Islam him and little Lum rims okay all
right so this is some copper talking
after many years of teaching he said you
know I realized the best thing that
helps students and has everything in it
is a little on me okay
got it okay that's the next part of your
class here even a single teaching
session devoted to the steps on the path
will cover every Buddhist teaching that
exists on this planet Oh Moneypenny
[Music]
yeah okay
I'm trying to at least finish this part
yeah and then he mentions the glia
Samaha which is a very famous Tantra and
he also mentions arias Angus a besom
alencar the jewel of realizations right
the first topic in the monastery for 12
years and and he says those books are
not complete they don't have all of
Buddhism in them you see the glorious
Imagi Tantra doesn't have the open
teachings in it and us might Reyes book
that we spent 12 years on doesn't have
the secret teachings in it but the larum
has both so he says if you think about
it its superior to the Tundra's and the
non temptress okay got it
who said that some copper okay when he
says a cool thing okay I'm just covering
roughly the paragraphs okay since we
have 25 minutes in which you are going
to look at nted and sleep with your eyes
open
and these Stevens got it down he's like
okay he says he says that way and this
way it's the best that way and this way
it's the best okay and it's very
interesting
let me get his strength
yeah if you study the alarm first you
can read all the other books of the
Buddha you see I mean it's like a key
that opens up all the other books okay
study the Lamia first ACI course number
one it will help you understand all the
other seventeen courses of the
foundation serious okay so the lahrman
is like a key to all the other courses
okay that means going from here to there
what about going from there to here yeah
everything out there all the Buddhist
teachings three hundred thousand books
in Tibetan are packed into this little
aluminum you can find them packed into
this number
okay got it so going that way if you
want to study pramana and you want to
study lower middle way or you want to
study higher mentally learn them lahrman
first and then that's the key to all
those doors and if you want to go from
all those doors back everything is
packed into this little poem fourteen
verses okay by the way I'll tell you
from personal experience I memorized a
song as work seventy five pages and
something happened to me afterwards I
just selling you on the idea of
memorizing this okay even in English you
can memorize or Chinese doesn't matter
memorize it in your language Spanish
doesn't matter but I'll tell you
something cool if you memorize a book
it's talking in your head all day long
okay and weird stuff happens to you okay
you have some copper talking in your
head you have Maitreya talking in your
head all day you know he's like and
you're like what I was thinking about
breakfast
you know and little pieces it's like
rock and roll songs they will come in
your head
Danny they in it then we listen that
this morning we're having fun on the way
here
oh come on Mike oh no sorry anyway
little snippets in English we call
snippets little pieces of this song
called three principal paths will they
just come in your mind and we you know
in the middle of argument with your
girlfriend and and it's our compasses
the path which pleases the body
surprises you're right so I've just tell
you from personal experience I didn't
nobody told me that I experienced it
okay and it's cool it's fun i if you
memorize a book by a Buddha it changes
your brain okay my brain by the way I
mean not to brag but it's getting
smarter every year you know I don't know
when it's gonna stop and I'll forget
things but there's a karma if you
memorize those books it does something
to your IQ and your IQ keeps it going on
okay it's kind of cool you should try it
it's kind of cool and then you can use
it for business and stuff you know
you're like better business person and
it makes you more capable if you have my
jewelry my trailer talking in your mind
all day okay
okay I'd like a rock and roll song I I
decided 50-50 is a good balance 50% rock
n roll songs in my head and 50% some
copper talking in my head that's my
suggestion okay
[Music]
yeah he's just selling the Lamia then he
does talk about the the first lamb in
Tibet which was the light on the pathway
la loire dr. Shah and then he says by
the way here he repeats what you learned
this morning I think it was this morning
who made the Longmen yeah
Buddha because it's called the Lamia
okay that's the proof okay interesting
okay good so traditionally if they ask
you for the source of the lamb rim
the answer is a portable a middle the
answer is the perfection of wisdom does
that refer to the lower middle of a
school no it refers to the tens of
thousands of pages ancient pages the
hundred thousand verses the the twenty
five thousand versions twenty thousand
verses the eight thousand verses the
diamond cutter Sutra which is sometimes
called the three hundred verses and you
know seven hundred it gets less and less
okay alright what's the shortest one you
catch it bar yeah oh there's a citron
which is called ah and it's one word and
it's so if you want some cocktail party
ammunition memorize that one go to the
cocktail party you see a cute boy say I
memorized the Sutra
he'll be impressed you don't have to
tell him it's okay all right and he
quotes the perfection of wisdom and he
says that's the source of the word Lum
room and I'll read it to you
it is this perfection nothing else which
is the path which is shared by all the
victors whether they are in the past the
present or the future this is the path
which all Buddha's have traveled past
present and future
this is the lamrim that's a quotation
from the perfection of wisdom sutras
okay anybody for $100 words like ding
[Music]
there's three things you can learn to do
in the class you know one is to sleep
with your eyes open you can smile as
well so good second level is nod your
head you know third level is only wake
up when getting lost $100 like word okay
now what was the hundred dollars yeah
okay here's the question he's like I'm
ready I'm ready
he's like he's like those Cowboys with
the gun I'm ready
that's the perfection of wisdom sutras
really possess the long room I mean
supposedly they are the source of the
Lama the ancient perfection of wisdom
Sutra spoken by Lord Buddha are supposed
to be the source of the long room but
are they really something
well if they did we wouldn't know not a
different answer see you again yeah you
can say that but there's a better answer
it's there's a problem here there's
stuff in the long room that isn't in the
perfection of wisdom mainly what's the
main topic of the profession was in
sutras yeah
the shortest one is the heart sutra for
example if you don't count ah okay
it's emptiness they don't talk about I
mean it's not the subject it's not
mainly bodhichitta of compassion it's
not okay so say bed then so I get my
money back right you're just sitting
there you just woke up for real say
Baden London didn't Morden I think
northern means explicit subject matter
okay obvious subject matter of the
perfection of wisdom sutras portabella
middle is is emptiness okay but
compassion is implied okay it's not
stated directly so when you study these
great scriptures we often talk about
what are the two levels in the scripture
what's the obvious level and what's the
underwater level okay what's going on
underneath and it's all compassion
okay got it so if you want to have a
debate on the debate ground you can say
that's the perfection of wisdom sutras
talk about both streams compassion and
emptiness and you can't lose the
argument if he says yes you can say no
it doesn't have compassion directly
stated if he says no you can say of
course it does it has both of them it's
a perfect debate question you you win
every way you can use this kind of logic
with your husband or wife
okay mmm so some Capablanca states that
the source of the word lamrim is that
quotation from the perfection of wisdom
sutras okay
that's a big deal okay and that's you
can answer people who say lahrman was
invented by the Lupus you know it's not
true it was invented by a another guy
okay
[Music]
then it goes off on not wasting your
time not invested what's the idiom by
the way ya glass flower because it's
beautiful and it's fragile
what is it yeah your mind don't mess
with your mind okay thank you okay so he
gives a verse from Sakya Pandita I think
yeah this is a great sakya lama the
first well not the first but weren't the
greatest of the sake lamas okay before
some kapa 200 years before some couple
during the time of the Mongols Chinggis
Khaan okay this junk jingus Khan's
nephew okay
go Duncan so anyway I'll read it to you
okay just for good luck I'm trying to
stall for 13 minutes even in okay anyway
I'll summarize it for you when you buy a
horse or a car okay nowadays it would be
your car you ask everybody you know you
save your money you ask everybody you
say you know I'm thinking to buy a car
you know and you ask all your friends
did you have it did you ever have a
Toyota yeah what was your experience
they suck forget it you know actually my
experience was very good I always buy
Toyotas okay but I don't know and I had
a good experience with a Honda okay and
then you can say you know Ford you avoid
afford whatever Chevrolet you know you
ask people you know it's the 2019 model
as good as the 2019 model you know I
don't want to buy the wrong car okay
same if you're gonna rent an apartment
you say is there coffee shops in the
place you know is it safe is the
neighborhood safe you ask people you see
people would buy a diamond often people
call me I've been out of the diamond
business for 20 exactly 20 years and
people still call me can you check this
diamond for me
because you know it's a big deal it's a
lot of money and and you don't know a
good diamond from a fake diamond you see
so when people make a big purchase they
always ask a lot of people this is sakya
pandita okay but when people buy some
Dharma they take anything like a hungry
dog you know anything they see on the
street they eat it fast you know he says
you all like hungry dogs you know
somebody comes into town somebody says
they're given initiation you run there
you pay your $35 you take a hi tantric
initiation which you weren't supposed to
be given unless you pass seven years of
course is and and you just gobble it
down
you don't ask if it's gonna make you
sick or okay like that he says we are
strange people we care more about our
car than our Dharma you know we'll take
any kind of Dharma we'll go into the
yoga class the teacher says let's
meditate over I don't know some weird
thing and you're like okay and we don't
we don't discriminate
we don't ask is that a good product or
not okay got it
and when he's trying to say is be more
picky be more picky be more demanding
don't just take any teaching someone
wants to give you okay it's the same
thing we talked about this morning maybe
you will get a mouthful of okay I was
sitting with my friend last night
after I ate that mob with tofu chocolate
King already and almost threw up and
they had a chocolate cake on a piece of
on a dish and they said gosh la this is
a real one this is not the mob with tofu
chocolate cake I'm like oh cool give me
a bite and I ate a big bite and it was
the mob with tofu chocolate
[Music]
like I'm so sorry
that's nice ed you're gonna gonna love
it though for hell you know
don't worry I'll come and get you all
right so sake Pilate says I don't take
anything again
okay danny has a quotation from Miller
Impa who's famous now a rapist
interesting guy
and I think it's important to know
something malaria is the most famous
meditator in tibet okay
everybody says that every tradition says
he was the most famous meditator in
tibet and his gore bloom his hundred
thousand songs which is a bad
translation of the title which because
it's not a hundred thousand songs it
just means a collection of songs it's
one of the most famous pieces of Tibetan
poetry like Daniels all nervous okay I I
hereby cleanse you of this bad deed he's
the one who gave me the kid okay
milarepa and the nice thing about
milarepa who became the most famous
meditator in tibet is that he didn't
start his serious meditation until he
was 50 okay
ten years after the average lifespan
okay nowadays it would be 80 okay he was
50 before he did his great retreats okay
so don't tell me you're too old to do
retreat or don't tell me you're too old
to start meditating okay you can teach
an old dog new tricks
okay it's possible it's always possible
to start don't say you're too old to
start meditation okay melih right by the
most famous meditator of all time was
fifty before he did his major and before
he started writing okay so Kumar
okay so do it
then he said and and I told you about
his poetry yesterday I think normal
Tibetan Potter's dun dun dun dun dun dun
dun
and you can tell milarepa without
knowing who wrote it because it goes
bomb dun dun dun that done time bomb
that done it so I translated it that way
okay here we go
the point that's the dump the point if
you don't meditate on advices passed
down from ear to ear or real tradition
real lineage the place the point the
place what about the place
it's like those hip hop song you can sit
in a mountain cave but you're just
torturing yourself
okay you can't sit in a cave in the
Himalayas and you can meditate but
you're wasting your time okay you're
just hurting your legs okay who said
that
yeah the greatest cave meditator of all
history said don't waste your time if
you don't have a good tradition if you
don't have a good oral tradition if it's
not an authentic scripture if it's not a
real teaching don't waste your time man
I've been there I've been in the
Himalaya caves you know I'm the number
one Himalaya kid dude I can't got it all
right I still got six minutes and I'm
gonna use it okay I'm ready to ask
homework the first homework question yay
I'm not gonna do the whole homework
tonight
really well I'm doing it at my own speed
and if you don't have a homework
tomorrow and you have to relax I'm
really sorry
okay three qualities of a book of a
practice someone tries to sell you a
meditation someone tries to sell you
with teaching it should have three
qualities if it doesn't have them don't
do it don't put it in your precious
real-estate okay don't break the glass
flower okay got it ready number one it
should have been taught by the Buddha
okay why why is that superior he's on
mission he knew you were reading the
book when he wrote the part got in okay
he was reading your mind when he wrote
the book maybe he knows what you need
number two and this is important
and I'd like to say something about the
Buddhist lineage okay
like I grew up Christian right I grew up
as a Christian and I studied Christian
my degree from Princeton is mainly
Christian studies and so I studied a lot
and there's a big tradition and I was
signed up to be a priest
I was already accepted by the the
seminary then I made the mistake to go
to India he and I never came back and
that's another story okay but uh in
Christianity in the study of
Christianity the farther back you go the
better the information is you see so
there's a big thing in Christian
Christian Studies at Princeton for
example to learn Greek learn Latin
I studied the Bible and Greek at Oxford
next Oxford okay we say in the town of
Oxford
but to be honest it wasn't Oxford
University but that the idea in
Christian studies is the further back
you go the more pure is the information
and I'll tell you something interesting
about Buddhist studies the closer you
come to pub unka for example the more
pure it is it's very interesting it's
very interesting if you really want to
understand Buddhism go backwards from
tsongkhapa or go backwards from banca
because they made it more clear because
they made it more and more clear more
and more easy to read more and more easy
to study ok and and I'll tell you
something you'll be very disappointed if
you try to read a perfection of wisdom
Sutra it's it's totally you can't
understand anything ok forget it don't
waste your time ok
that will be the last thing we ever
translate in this school will be the
Buddhist own sutras except for the heart
sutra diamond concept okay but if you
translate the perfection with some
sutras and you publish it no one will
understand it at all ok you need you
need each generation of explanation ok
you cannot read combination oh forget it
karma Sheila has not been taught in 1300
years that I'm aware of you can't read
it forget it
you need some karma and you need pop
unka and you need ACI okay because it
becomes more and more clear okay then
you can understand the next generation
bag so it's the opposite of the
Christian studies you see what I mean in
this tradition the more years that went
by that better that presentation became
more and more clear okay it's really
weird it's really weird okay so if you
start a translation committee or
something
go for the go for the Tony Lamas maybe
go for the takapa if you spent 30 years
doing it but don't go past then you know
you will you won't understand it okay
it's too difficult okay so in this
tradition as the years went by it got
more pure and more clear and that's the
second advice of what book to read okay
here's the second advice read books
which have been through the process of
purifying by each generation okay
read the recent books read some copper
read pop Anka
read AC I read DCI okay that's the
suggestion the second suggestion what
was the first suggestion yes take the
things that Lord Buddha talked about but
study at through a tradition where the
presentation was made more and more
accessible each generation okay and by
the way the presentation of chandrakirti
was clear to people in his time
according to Buddhism people get
stupider in the last 2,000 years
every generation just because they
didn't have cars and airplanes don't
think the older generations were stupid
they weren't they memorize the book
while the Buddha taught it we can't do
it you see I mean so chandrakirti's
commentary is clear to historians and
Buddhist sutras are clear to his
students but they're not clear to us you
need a recent commentary okay got it
so that's the second advice okay go
backwards through the generations who
made it more accessible to you okay
don't forget the relationship between
accurate and accessible otherwise you're
making chocolate mud with tofu cakes
okay God in make your presentation as an
ACI teacher accessible modern sexy
interesting play rock and roll
you have to can you get me Tim by
tomorrow the guy who did Mayday in
Taiwan
you can ask Scott okay I need some video
of the guy who did Mayday in Taiwan okay
you do video okay Carrie shot tomorrow
tomorrow evening okay she has right I
don't mind when you do rock and roll it
doesn't matter okay so make it fun make
it accessible okay but don't corrupt it
don't corrupt it don't say the four
principle path or the two principal
paths don't fix that just play rock and
roll and teach T okay
okay last thing the third requirement of
a good Buddhist teaching don't don't
open your mind to this teaching unless
it was taught by the Buddha or comes
from the Buddha and secondly it's been
passed on in a pure way okay thirdly
there should be people who used it and
got the results there should be success
stories there should be what we call
testimonials there should be people if
this going on for 2,000 years and nobody
saw emptiness then maybe we should
cancel it he said I mean like didn't
happen to anybody
did anybody who studied tantrum ain't
manjushri face to face or Virginia
guinea diamond angel
gingka you Jamal did somebody meet her
not you know and the answer is yes in
our lineage okay par banca chuja
remember J mu Qi Donald Bhadra
tsongkhapa all these dis met her because
they studied the ancient tantric courses
so you understand okay so that's the
third requirement okay it should have
worked for people and they passed it on
to the next generation those two parts
of the third one okay here I go
it should have worked for people there
should be evidence that it worked for
people and then secondly what work for
them they should have told their
students and so for example spiritual
partner you know Lord Buddha had tilith
Amma some Kaaba had hung Shama then
pop-punk remember till he had his own
Biagio Guinea and they pass it on they
really happened to them they met her
they studied with her she trained them
ok there's a real stories there's real
books about their conversations and
stuff so we want this kind of really
work for somebody there should be some
really work for something ok so that's
your first homework question
unfortunately you won't be able to do
your homework tomorrow and I have to
write the part about the four courses
that we covered and they get a period
how long on each of course I won't do
all them I'll sneak it in ok and it's in
your reading it's in your manual ok all
the information in email but the first
homework question for the day after
tomorrow the day after your big rest day
is I mean kind of rest day I think TMS
stuff from you what are the three
qualities of a good Buddhist teaching
number one Buddha taught it number two
yeah it got more and more pure it's been
it's been got more and more clear people
cleaned out the stuff that people added
ok like somebody asked me to translate
yoga Sutra it was very difficult it was
very frustrating it's clear to me them
most of the fourth chapter was added by
other people and there's many scriptures
like that you don't see them in Buddhism
you don't see sutras where people added
stuff you don't see it ok people don't
do that ok and then third one
there should be some success stories
there should be success stories okay got
it all right that's a good Buddhist book
will continue that tomorrow all right
we're going to finish class four I gave
you a little vacation yesterday I tried
to teach the whole thing slowly and it's
not going to work so we're just gonna go
mainly focus on the Masters on the
homework masters and you know you can
read the text yourself this is probably
the longest reading of all the ACI
courses because I was lazy I didn't
translate anything for the course I just
put my old translation which I already
published in the course so I didn't have
to do anything but it's long okay the
other courses are not so long okay all
right we reached 400 verses written by I
edema okay
they say he was a student of Nagarjuna
Arya Nagar Jinnah or maybe he was close
and he wrote a very famous book about
emptiness called four hundred verses
probably I guess around three or 400 AD
okay and in there he describes the death
because we did the definition of a
teacher so now we have to do the
definition of a student yeah what are
the student students qualities okay and
this is traditional in the long room
before you study the Lamia you talk
about what's a qualified teacher and
then the teacher gets to say yeah but
what's a qualified student okay so then
they have a nice list of the qualities
of a student this is probably the
shortest list it only has three parts
okay
there are many other lists that are very
long but you know the goal of a CI
course one is to present these things in
a in 10 classes the whole Buddhism okay
so we can't go into big lists okay here
we go
first call this a sore knee do you know
certainly you know
sure yeah sword means corner and it also
means X like X abot cancer remember J
means X it means in the corner no longer
active okay and they're so cool we
talked about this morning surname means
open mind and it means you don't take a
position you you go to the class a good
student in Long Room comes to the class
with the open mind
okay and and they by the way doesn't
mean they accept everything no not at
all
but they listen okay they listen so they
are unbiased if surname is unbiased they
walk into the class they are open okay
they're open for new ideas that's how
they approach the class that's the
attitude they have when they come to the
class they are open to new ideas okay
and Maitreya said yeah don't accept them
right away you know ask questions see if
it fits
see if it fits what you know there are
three famous tests for $100 they are
gold gold I like the gold there's three
actions and three meanings there are
unions let somebody else try
well we we Bernie
cut it and file it okay burn it fine cut
it and file it yeah but what are those
refer to three tests of new information
how to check new information I'm like I
don't remember myself we had it in CSP
say again
take it yeah
does it conflict with something the
teacher said earlier okay if the teacher
said on Friday don't eat meat and then
on Saturday says it mean then it doesn't
pass the third test okay what's the
first one yeah it's this your own
experience like yeah I noticed when I
eat meat I feel terrible and my
cholesterol goes up and there must be
some bad karma Darren okay what's the
second one cutting logic yeah use logic
you know does it make sense does it make
sense okay is it logical okay so those
are the three tests all right so a
student is soon a they walk into the
room open they have an open mind and
they check but still they check
everything okay which is part of the
second quality of a student say London
London
it means smart high IQ but what kind of
IQ yeah spiritual IQ and you know I'll
tell you honestly when I started the ACI
courses in New York this course the
first course I think we had five people
or six people and I was giving out the
homeworks that's the first time anyone
gave homeworks for a Buddhist class and
I noticed there's two kinds of people
you know one kind they always get
hundred on their homeworks but they're
very irritating yeah like they're the
most unfriendly person in the class
they're very smart and if you say the
best teacher gets the highest score then
they would be the best teacher
they got all hundreds but they're
irritating people and they're not nice
to the students and then there's people
who got 90 and 89 and they didn't they
weren't number
in the homework category but they were
number one in the nice to other people
category which is a ACI teacher
okay got it um I think those are two
different kinds of IQ that's two
different kinds of IQ you know in
America we learn to take tests I was
really good at tests I was the number
one student in Arizona my scores were
the highest yeah my year and I went to
meet the president so there's a kind of
intelligence for taking tests but it
doesn't mean you have emotional
intelligence or or kindness that's a
different kind of IQ so here we're
talking about the second kind of IQ you
know are you spiritually high IQ okay
and by the way there's an ancient test
in the magic mecca of a time of
spiritual IQ for zero dollars because I
think he might get it okay I will offer
money no I won't yeah they say they
start to cry in the class sometimes and
a boot on one put down one mean see you
get goose bumps like there starts
talking about emptiness in your neck
just it's like when - like it's a yoga
so if you have a high spiritual IQ and
they start talking about emptiness and
you're like okay it's like listening to
your favorite song and they say they
start to cry people if you have a real
seed you were crying the class so don't
try to cry in the class okay you can
hide the onion in your in your hider
onion in your person everyone will think
you have a higher thank you
okay all right
that's why I also puts onions right oh
he gave me his mother's enchiladas I
went to heaven last night okay
third quality of a student's a danira
big vision big vision okay big vision
I'm talking other planets okay you're
the kind of person who likes to go out
at night at Diamond Mountain and stand
for a while okay you can go back and
look at your phone later but there is a
world out here it has stars you know
it's not 2 inches by 4 inches where most
people live and go out and look at the
Stars and think big say num cup bunny
jump across the sky
it's a beautiful word jump across the
sky okay it means think big okay this
ACI teacher training you know we're
talking the professors in we're talking
every lunchtime and I we have a feeling
that if this the teacher training goes
well it's going to quickly spread to
many places we just never organized it
before now we're trying to organize it
and so have this kind of vision okay
Daniela Daniela means you have a big
vision in mind big vision in mind okay
you want to help every person on this
planet okay and and again it doesn't
mean that every person becomes a Tibetan
Buddhist it doesn't mean that okay it
means people start using the force terms
people start using these ideas that you
can become successful by sharing and by
giving to others and then hopefully the
whole thing becomes the culture in the
world and people forget who started it
got it that's my goal you know I want
the culture of the world to change and I
want to change the culture of other
planets and I want everyone to forget
who started it okay got it
who started sidewalks
Benjamin Franklin who started public
libraries Benjamin Franklin and that's
cool is it most people don't know it
used to be you couldn't you had to be
extremely wealthy to own one book
because they had to be written by hand
on vellum parchment and only rich people
had books and they would never let other
people read them and then he's like
let's all the rich people put their
books in a building and we'll control it
and people can borrow it you know he had
this idea and now I don't know at least
in this country probably all over the
world there's public libraries you can
go in and check out a book and they
forgot who started it okay so that's the
goal we want to be spiritual Benjamin
Franklin where's his picture and a
hundred dollar bill okay not the one
dollar bill he's on the that's proof
he's cool all right
we finished class four